this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software hello this is the immedi
Spinelli's for software engineering
radio today I have with me Kirk
Pepperdine and I will be talking with
him on performance optimization Kirk
Pepperdine has been working in
high-performance and distributed
computing for nearly 20 years his focus
has primarily been on performance
working on architecting developing
including applications running on Cray
and other high-performance computing
platforms Kirk know specializes in Java
where he works in all aspects of
performance and tuning in each phase of
a project lifecycle Kirk was recognized
in 2006 as Java champion Kirk welcome to
software engineering radio thank you for
having me here
so what should developers encountering
and performance problems start their
investigation
that's how is a good question a lot of
people have trouble you know knowing
where to start they get a lot of
confusing information from a lot of
different sources and it really takes
some time to you know understand what
all of this information means and put it
into some contact so it all makes sense
because generally what I find is that
all the information even the stuff that
looks contradictory tends to make sense
but only after you know what's happening
prior to you understanding what's going
on it tends to be very very confusing so
this is one of the reasons why I
developed a model because the the model
helps me understand what's going on in
the system it it basically allows me to
take all of that all of these signals
dump it into the model and then the
model helps me make sense of it so I
call us my
you know performance diagnostic model
now you briefly described what it
involves well you know it's like any
other model the model has something
representing all of the components of
the system in it and from that I can
help me it helps me to understand what
each of the components are responsible
for and what their interactions are and
so when you run into some performance
issue you can look at the signals you
can put it in and you can say okay which
components would possibly be responsible
for these types of signals and each of
the components are distinct in the sense
that they are responsible for certain
sets of signals and by using this
particular model what I can actually do
then is take these signals plugging in
and it helps me to at from a you know
top-down point of view tunneled down
like through the layers of you know
complexity to get to where the root
cause is here give us a concrete example
yeah sure absolutely I was contacted by
this one company just a wild while ago
and they said we need to have our
garbage collectors tuned and I said okay
cool
I can do that no problem I need garbage
collection logs because the garbage
collection logs are going to provide me
with the visibility I need into what the
garbage collector is doing and so you
know I said here's how you collect them
they did all that they sent me the
garbage collection log I started the
analysis on the garbage collection log
and I looked at it and says mmm garbage
collectors are working fine there is not
an issue with the garbage collectors in
this particular application there's in
other words I could tune the garbage
collectors from now till whenever things
are not going to get better because that
wasn't the primary problem with the with
the application and and then the garbage
collector you know the garbage
collection logs sort of also act as what
I call a proxy metric
for other things that are happening in
your application and this falls a little
all under the box of memory how does
your application consume and churn and
basically interact with memory right
are you memory efficient or a memory
inefficient do you have large live sets
are they stable do you have small lie
sets do you turn a lot you know so those
types of questions in this case what I
found was that was that the application
was very memory inefficient and you
can't tune a garbage collector to make
up for an applications memory
inefficiency you have to go back to the
application and tune it so should
developers start at a higher level look
at some high level things first and then
focus on particular areas well you know
I always ask the question okay so what
are the essays that are being missed
what are the conditions in the
environment so what are the signals that
the environment is giving us and then
I'm gonna look at the you know look
under the look at those conditions right
so what are the SLA is being missed look
at the conditions in the environment for
the components that are responsible for
you meeting those particular SLA s and
I'll use those signals to try to sort
out what the root causes so in the case
of this particular company I knew I
could use the garbage collection log as
a proxy measure for certain aspects of
application efficiency and as it turns
out you know how other aspects of
performance right so the the garbage
collection logs can act as a proxy
measure of this whole thing so when I
saw that the garbage collector itself
seemed to be running fine then you have
to look at the workload and the workload
in this case was enormous and I said
okay fine you know you know so we have
to go down that route
the way I got there was by basically
saying yeah I'm gonna look at the
specific signal but then I'm gonna step
back and when I step back I'm gonna look
at the overall picture and you know
there are indicators in the garbage
collection log that in this case helped
me understand what was going on that's
not always the case right but in general
what you want to do is you want to get
down to some key core metrics and you
want to use those key core metrics to
help you get an understanding of what
the overall condition is in the runtime
that's causing the problem and then use
that information to basically tunnel
down or focus on identifying what the
problem is what would these metrics be
well most of them are just simply
Hardware metrics and these are really
cheap and easy to get so one of the
things I do is identify what I call the
dominating consumer the CPU that
activity or the condition inside the CPU
that's dominating how the CPU can be
consumed and you get into two different
conditions you get into passive
dominance and you'll get into aggressive
dominance sit res yeah well passive
dominance is the harder one for people
to recognize and the one that they miss
out on most often but it's some
condition in the run time that's
preventing the CPU from being consumed
so if I if I have identified passive
dominance as being a problem that I'm
gonna look for conditions that could
cause the runtime to prevent the CPU
from being consumed and of course
aggressive dominance is you can imagine
from that definition is that I am just
doing something that's just basically
saturating the CPU could you give us
some concrete examples so that people
can relate to them yeah here's a simple
one I have an undersized thread pool in
my application server mm-hmm okay I have
a whole pile of requests coming in and
so you know where's the blah
well I can't get a thread to be
processed and they can't get a thread to
be processed because you know there just
simply aren't enough threads in the
thread pool when you look at hardware in
that in the under those conditions what
you're gonna see is that the hardware is
being underutilized so what I have are
exceptionally long response times if you
look at the time budget on the thread
you're gonna see that the majority of
the time budget is gonna be spent in the
thread pool basically just blocked
waiting to get a thread right right and
you're gonna see the hardware's
underutilized mm-hmm let's flip that
around exactly what's the other case
well not the other case let's flip it
around and you know what does that look
like to you know like an Operations
person that's looking at their
application they see they're not meeting
the SLA so they have SLA violations and
they don't know why right so what is the
information that they have that can lead
them to the path of understanding that
the thread pool needs sighs needs to be
increased well generally it's going to
be look at the hardware counters and
you're gonna see that I have all of this
load coming in onto the system about my
CPUs are under you under utilized and
that's usually some signal of some
congestion someplace and in this case
there's a very easy trick to discover
what's going on and that's simply do a
thread dump and when you look at the
thread dump you're gonna look at see
that all of the threads in the thread
pool or the connection pool or you know
database pool or you know whatever it is
whatever the pool is they're all going
to be busy right doing something and if
you see that the all of the threads in
your thread pool are always busy doing
something then that's a pretty clear
indication that it's under sized I see
other particular tools you recommend for
getting these details yeah sure and he
serves like really cheap and easy I can
use J CMD free tool comes with the JDK
right
so if I do just J command on the command
line it gives me a list of all of giv
M's I can communicate with if I do a
dash help it you know with the pit of
the JVM of interest it tells me all the
operations that that JVM will support
one of them will be you know print you
know print stock dump and I can just
execute it and after that it's a text
file so there's tools like TDA which you
can use it's a thread dump analysis tool
and you just load the data into that and
you can just Splunk around and and just
you know just simply be curious that's
all
you have the data be curious so you're
assuming the application is
multi-threaded but that's not always the
case so when the application is not
multi-threaded you have to start from a
different perspective I assume well you
have to adjust the model again you have
to look at it you know if you know and
we've worked with applications that are
purposely single-threaded right so event
comes in event loop takes event
processes it type thing but it's always
single threaded we've done this on a
number of occasions so you have to
adjust some model you have to look at
this and say okay this is single
threaded by nature so in one case we had
a 24 core box using like 1 core for
processing single threaded we just
adjust the model and say okay single
threaded I can only consume one CPU so
I'm going to just adjust the model and
say ok based that I'm using only one CPU
let's do the exact same analysis am i
able to consume that CPU or am I not
mm-hmm and you often see that you are
because you mean it or that you are
waiting and then how do you proceed from
that point onwards to find the real
culprit well depend that depends on on
you know if I'm you consuming it or if
I'm waiting it if I'm consuming it then
I have an algorithmic strength issue and
then what I have to do
I have to find some way to reduce the
algorithmic strength now that can come
from the garbage collector is overactive
that could come from the application is
memory inefficient that could come from
just you know the algorithms I'm using
or just you know too expensive and I
need to find something that's I need to
go through some strength reduction in
that case in order to to try to try to
do something in in one case we looked at
the workflow and we said some of this
work doesn't need to be done all the
time
mm-hmm so we took it out and that's cool
because you know shorter execution paths
take less time to execute so simply
doing less was the answer now we added
new events to the system to do the stuff
that needed to be done occasionally and
in in that in that case that helped
quite a bit it took you know in this
case it took our the idle loop and made
it you know two to three percent more
idle which is good because we wanted all
of the incoming events to be executed
almost immediately the only way you're
gonna have something executed almost
immediately or immediately is to have a
waiting thread for it if you only have
one thread that means that that one
thread needs to spend a lot of its time
being idle I see and somehow you can now
adjust this modulation for applications
that deal mostly with Network cores for
example to the rest applications yeah in
those cases this model also works in
this case because you'll see indications
that you're too reliant on the network
or others see I guess the common
anti-pattern performance ng pattern is
what's known as revolving door and
revolving door is basically well it
comes from EJB right where we had a
client nad being or whatever session
being whatever it doesn't matter but you
have you have basically have a client
and a server and you need to get the
data from
from the server so I'm just gonna do
like get X get Y get said mm-hmm and so
on so I make all of these really really
really really small Network calls and of
course that's gonna put a lot of stress
on the kernel so that's gonna pop the
kernel x and you can see that in the in
the CPU counters another common thing is
hibernate and what's known as ripple
loading and that's really a case where
you should do like you you're
essentially doing a table joint right
mm-hmm and you probably should do the
table joint in the database but what
hibernate is going to do is it's going
to basically do select star from table X
for every element in table X a select
column well select data from table Y and
join it in memory right right so this is
um this is like a revolving door pattern
so I'm just gonna and and you know and
of course the duration is linear to the
size of table X some number of calls you
make right so you get all kinds of like
bad things happening in terms of
performance but the big telltale sign is
that you're gonna really hammer the
kernel and the kernel is not gonna like
this and if you hammer the kernel you
are going to limit the scalability of
your application and in this case you
know if you consider that every network
call takes a millisecond and you do a
thousand live these I mean then you have
a floor on your response time which is
you know in this case one second and it
and quite often we don't see that it's
like you know a thousand calls it's
generally more like a hundred thousand
calls or you know something larger than
that which means that you know the
response times now are hundreds of
seconds right so you let me switch
through there all of databases would you
look at the database performance from
the database side or from the
application side where we can to look at
things here's here's where you start
getting confusing information if you
have a good database guy and he knows
what he's doing
what you're gonna find is that he's
gonna come back to you in these cases
and say look guys we're clearing
transactions you know without any issue
no problems in our part right but you
know of course you're gonna have your
end-user saying like but-but-but and you
know probably a lot of the metrics are
gonna say yeah it's a database problem
but it is a really database problem if
you're trying to make a hundred thousand
calls when all you really need to do is
issue a join and get the results you
want right I mean this isn't saying you
know write your business logic in sequel
it just basically means you know you
have to still be intelligent about the
number of network calls you're making
because that is an expensive resource
and you know yada yada yadi about about
network stuff you know all that aside
database performance is generally very
very very good databases are generally
not a performance issue if you use them
properly in this case you know hibernate
ripple loading is a perfect example of
how to abuse the database and you're not
really abusing the database what you're
doing is you're abusing your network
stack all right so our object relational
mapping approach is part of the problem
or part of the solution what's your
experience in this or yes you mentioned
hibernate hibernate is a good product it
solves a particular issue and if it's
used properly and people understand it
who use it then I don't have any issues
with hibernate yeah you know the it's
it's got its issues of course and you
have to do all kinds of you know wacky
things to to deal with the issues but
that's not hibernates fault that's
basically trying to get around the
problem that we don't have a real good
global identity system for object
systems and that's a completely
different topic yeah we can talk about
that key text should be later on
yeah well that's even goes beyond
architecture that's just you know well I
mean we talk I've talked about this
marker services talk span you know I
mean if you need to maintain
if you need to need to maintain the the
property of singularity in your systems
then you need to have proper identity
and as soon as you do distributed
computing you lose you lose identity
which means you lose singularity which
means that you pick up a whole host of
problems because of that
hibernate just makes it a lot easier for
the uninitiated to run into this problem
one last thing regarding databases often
colleagues tell me that they have a not
so clear database schema not normalized
no to achieve high performance but then
the database schema suffers so how do
you resolve this tension between clear
database schema and high performance in
my experience I've not really seen this
happen in other words if you have a good
database person and you come to them and
say look this is what we're trying to do
generally they'll come up with a schema
with the appropriate indexing that will
result in the database not being an
issue in the few cases where it is is an
issue caching is your friend mm-hmm that
petition site right yes on the
application side obviously and there's
some very very good products that that
are able to do this you know I I don't
want to mention any of them because the
other guys will get upset by this but in
general they all come with their pluses
and minuses but in general they all do a
good job of me you know if something is
expensed too expensive to acquire then
you know the obvious answer is cache it
if you can I see okay we can discuss now
architecture so how important is
software architecture for an
applications performance you mentioned
this below but that antibodies from
there why there issues here it's
critical work performance if you don't
come up with a good solid basis from the
beginning then it's very likely that
your system will never perform no matter
what you do to it you know in my mind
just really taking care to look at
architecture from the beginning is kind
of important I know that sounds sort of
non
agile but I would tend to disagree I
think that the that if you look at some
of the more well architected systems
that are out there today the the shops
are very agile and you know agile
doesn't mean you know scrums agile and
all of this other stuff doesn't mean we
don't plan it it just means that we plan
in a different way all right so all of
this work has to fit into some sort of
framework and that that's generally what
we call architecture so there must be
some architectural goals in mind when
you start now you might have to be
flexible on some of these but you know
in general some of the more modern
architectures certainly the type of
architectures that micro services and
cloud environments are favoring I in my
experience have tended to be the most
scalable and the most performant for
most classes of problems not all but
most classes of problems if they're done
properly
isn't that a danger to other architect
or I click in the wrong direction if you
start thinking about performance from
day one yeah you know it's kind of funny
um there's certain things that you want
to consider when you're architecting but
I I think the first thing you need to do
is make sure that you have a functional
product you know having the fastest app
on the planet that no one uses isn't
very useful obviously yes right in in my
mind I mean even even the stuff I write
I'm going to use architectural designs
that I know are going to help me tune
this thing if I need to tune it but
generally performance is a secondary
concern what I'm starting off in a
project if I've architected it so that I
can do things to the application
afterwards easily then you know I'm
gonna be satisfied with that you know so
some of the things you know follow good
coding principles make sure the things
that are coupled that need to be coupled
or coupled make sure the things that
should be loosely coupled
they're loosely coupled worried about
complexity you know those are the two
biggest things I think that that people
should take away if I mean tuning is a
debugging process you have a regression
a performance regression somebody's
gonna have to go in there and refactor
code so you want to make it easier for
them from their textual point of view
okay I have a bug you know one plus one
equals three I need to go find it
same issue isn't it really regarding
particular particular choices such as
the JVM or containers or micro-services
how do you think they affect performance
you mentioned micro-services I think is
a good thing and they always working
like that I've seen some have overheads
associated with them yeah of course they
actually do you know again we don't have
what I would call a global identity
system so as we punch data around
clusters we do a number of horrible
things the you know one of the horrible
things we do is we have basically copies
of data and you know copies of the same
thing so we've lost singularity and
we've lost identity on a cluster wide
basis so you know that's an issue right
but that's a consistency issue more than
a performance issue the performance
issues come when we pass data around you
know the the the most common scheme to
pass data around these days is Jason
right and you know we're using an
incredibly sparse representation of our
data so that means takes up a lot of
space and we're using some very
expensive for the most probably the most
expensive resources in our system in
order to push this data around you know
I think of it this way right if I have
if it takes me like a milli second to
get a message from one service to
another right so and a millisecond is is
is a good thing I mean you also have a
lot of other what I call ancillary
effects of in the in the act of getting
the data from one place to another you
know if you have like even like a two
gigahertz processor sitting in a machine
you know my question is how many
operations can you complete in one
millisecond with that processor it's not
something to be smeared no absolutely
not
so the decision to offload the
processing to another service or consume
it yourself or you know just do it
yourself
I mean you have to look at it and you
have to answer that question is it worth
distributing this particular message or
should I just do this myself and what
are the consequences of each choice so
you're saying that micro-services you
can overdo the amount of splitting you
do is this what you're getting at well
let's
well microservices is is an
architectural style and a way of doing
things you know so there's all kinds of
things that help people you know it's
it's basically a way of operations as
not just an architectural style right so
but from an architectural style point of
view then you know it's the same as any
other distributed system yeah you can
easily get into a revolving door effect
but like carefully they can help towards
achieving better efficiency applied
carefully
they're amazing it's the first large
service based architecture that I worked
on was a number of years ago mm-hm
and at that time you know I mean the
architecture really came because we just
didn't have any other way I mean you
could not stovepipe this application it
just wouldn't work so you know that
service-oriented architecture really
came out of a necessity you know it was
the only way that we could do things but
when we're passing data around we're
passing around big chunks of data that
took significant amounts of time to
process
and you know because of that we didn't
really have any of these you know while
we didn't have good networks not like
today but we didn't suffer from any of
the problems that you would have because
of you know all of them the network
activity mostly because the proportion
of network activity to you know
computation was just so high that you
knew then the network was below the
noise floor in in the in the equation
right and and I think that's really one
thing you want to make sure is you want
to make sure that the network noise is
in the is in the noise floor in terms of
the overall computational costs because
it's overhead right yeah it's just pure
overhead absolutely pure overhead and
you want to try to you know amortize you
know that cost so if you do it that way
you can get amazing results absolutely
amazing we were also event-driven and
event-driven you know and this was in
the era before I mean we didn't call it
solo or microwave or anything like that
because we didn't have those words to
describe what we're doing you know
yeah these words just simply didn't
exist but we were conceptually we had a
lot of the same concepts obviously the
tools today are different and better and
micro services in terms of a philosophy
or a way of getting things done didn't
exist so we didn't have any of those
tools so we knew I can't really call it
micro services but you know it was
certainly so and you know the benefits
of that particular architecture being
event-driven and service-oriented have
basically stuck with me you know since
since since that time and to see this
you know trend emerging where we have
like event-driven designs and large
soy-based applications and now micro
services to me just seems like a natural
progression from a lot of the lessons
that we learned in in our particular
application there's it just makes your
system so much more flexibility it puts
you into a position where you can
actually experiment with different
things you can run the experiments
faster at a greater rate to do them in
your
environments not in test environments
where you gonna get it wrong the the
advantages just go on and on and on so
for I would say the vast majority of
applications on the planet this type of
architecture is just you know the bee's
knees as they say so this is something
our listeners should remember you
mentioned earlier garbage collection
which brings it to the topic of
programming languages so people often
claim that the specific programming
language is less efficient than other I
have the discussion regarding I'll show
the colleague who told me a case where
rails was 100 times more expensive than
production settings and a JVM
alternative so should the underlying
language be primarily concerned when
choosing applications platform no I
don't think so I think people are when
they focus on performance they're
actually focusing on the wrong thing
mm-hmm
you have to look at you know what's
expensive in deploying a system you know
what takes time where are the problems
coming from and and most of the problems
are coming from developers being unable
to express themselves in code right now
is that a problem of the developers mmm
you could argue yes but I could will
also argue no so I'm gonna take the nose
side here not a problem developers it's
a problem of the language is ability to
allow the developer to express himself
uh-huh okay can you give us an example
yeah off the top of my head well you can
just think of okay right guys so let's
go back prior to Java prior to je prior
to all these things distributing
distributed computing was the realm of
you know high performing specialty teams
not a day to day everyday developer post
Java distributed systems are normal and
even mediocre developers are building
distributed systems you may ask why in
my opinion it's because of the languages
the tooling nje and all of these things
that have allowed the developers to be
come more expressive that's what's
important there are more project more
productive they're building larger
systems and they could before and you
don't need a team of rock star
developers to get interesting things
done normal people or normal developers
can work on problems that were
unreachable even you know 15 years ago
so you're saying there is an effect of
the language but it has more to do with
how it allows programmers to express
themselves in a higher style that can be
more efficient or than low-level details
such as the cost of garbage collection
or something like that absolutely
absolutely
you know you know the fact that we have
these problems with garbage collectors
because of systems doing this that or
the other thing you know we didn't have
these problems in the past because
people just are able to get to you
weren't doing the things that they're
doing today simply because they didn't
have the tools and languages and and
support that they needed in order to be
able to do this is the these things that
are that we consider to be hard or you
know before they were impossible
and I mean and that's that's what's
happening in this industry right we make
the hard and the difficult easy and by
doing so we make the impossible possible
and we make the possible less difficult
and then you see another people have to
reach but languages are also improving I
understand so things that were
inefficient in the past are less so
presumably you have seen many
improvements in Java implementations
over the years um yeah sure I mean you
know my my whipping post has always been
how bad logging is in Java and it's
horrible
it is absolutely dreadfully bad and the
lard for Jade guys did something to make
that better so that got better I think
Jay ease gotten better over the years
you know spring didn't like the early
implementations of je and
it transformed how we write code you
know so you I mean you see all kinds of
improvements coming from all over the
place there are some improvements being
done at the lower lever at the JVM level
oh yeah absolutely absolutely as people
learn more they they go back in and
adjust things we used to have a big
problem with simple things that people
wouldn't even think of called
nepotism inside the JVM inside the JDK
classes you know and this is where
objects get distributed across
generations mm-hmm and when they get
distributed across dinner generations
then you get things that are well you
get zombies because these are objects
that are kept live because of the
properties of the garbage collector but
you know these these objects are alive
but they're not live they should be
garbage collected but they can't be
because of the mechanics of the garbage
collector and you know so people figure
this out and they've gone back into the
JDK and they've made adjustments in the
code where these conditions can be
adjusted for and as a developer you
don't have to think about this because
now you can use that data structure and
things work better so as a developer
what should you think if you are
developing java application how can you
give the JVM more chances to optimize
your code or to work with your code in
the most efficient manner
right simple code that's the best thing
you can do those three words right
simple code it is something that many of
us have been saying now for decades
almost forever right simple code right
so there's no need to think about the
internals or what happens in specific
cases just write the most simple and
readable code pot you can think of
that's exactly right pay attention to
the api's make sure you're writing good
stable api's that don't cause other
people to do bad things in order to have
to use your API I'm talking about api's
we can discuss a bit about algorithms so
nowadays most algorithms come packaged
in libraries or
system software use a database or data
structures does this mean that
developers will rarely favor a need to
implement algorithmic code days have we
left the world of algorithms the time of
algorithms that we need to think about
them as far as implementation goes I'm
not sure we're ever going to leave them
behind
certainly we spend less of our time on
writing technical infrastructure such as
you know different algorithms for doing
different sorts and things like that and
that's what I was thinking yeah in
general that's a good thing you know
because I'm either writing certain code
or I'm writing business logic and of
course the thing that's gonna bring
value to my employer is gonna be the
business logic right so the more time I
spend there as opposed to spending
writing you know technical
infrastructure then of course that's
gonna be a win so yes we are moving to
we are spending less and less time
thinking about algorithms and things
like that you know like sorting and
stuff like that but I don't think we're
ever gonna get rid of it I think you
know as technology progresses there's
there's going to be new things that we
can do to make things better
and which means that we'll have to dive
back into algorithms to adjust the
algorithms so that they make better use
of the new features that are presented
even in hardware then still know about
algorithmic complexity and take it into
account oh they are well they add the
apps just because they don't have to
right it doesn't mean they shouldn't
know about it I mean you should know
what it means when you decide to use a
linked list over an ArrayList these
under knees are right you know you
should know fundamentally what the
differences are and what the
implications of using either one are in
terms of performance right so you can
choose the best data structure for the
problem so data layouts again for most
applications is you know this has
marginal
I know like people like Martin Thompson
would be just cringing when he hears me
say this yeah and I and I completely get
what he's saying he says you know the
industry is hugely wasteful and on one
end it is it's we're hugely wasteful of
computing resources and we can do tons
better in terms of coming up with better
data structure layouts in order to make
better efficient more efficient use of
our hardware but I don't think that's
the point I think the real constraining
resource is people and we need to figure
out better ways to make use of our
people resources and if that means that
we're gonna throw away hardware to do it
well you know sorry Martin but I value
people more than Hardware all right
interesting yes yeah I'm not sure that
Martin will disagree with me on that
particular point so yeah so don't take
this to beat rollin Martin I have a lot
of respect from the guy is incredibly
close you know clever and people
absolutely need to listen to him and
take into account his mechanical
sympathy movement I think it's it's a
fantastic thing let's he's and what he's
uh you know what he's done and in
bringing this out so the wrong way you
mentioned throwing hardware resources
which brings you to a discussion about
hardware architecture over the past
years CPU speeds have been stagnant and
we only seen a number of cores
increasing the will this mean we get
more emphasis on code performance we can
no longer expect our mistakes or
inefficiencies the code to be plastered
over through higher CPU speeds ok so I'm
going to go back to quoting Martin here
but this time in a good way he did a
study which I found very interesting he
says you know in 2005 clock speeds
flattened out and therefore you know we
went to taking all of the gates and well
that we can put onto a chip and we
started getting them to use
getting them to do something else we
didn't actually add more cores but
that's a different story there's a
reason why we didn't add more course
well well as some people say you know
before I give you two cores you should
learn how to use one right right well
you know so they've given us like
basically well for all intents and
purposes eight cores on a laptop and you
know how many people actually use all
eight so we don't need more course what
we actually need is faster memory and
memory is really the huge bottleneck
yeah but that said Martin did this very
interesting experiment and it was very
clever of them to be able to to be able
to do this
he took an application and got a whole
bunch of different generations at
different CPUs and he ran that
application on all these CPUs and what
he found is that the retirement rates
for CPU instructions actually was still
following Moore's law against all of
these CPUs even though the clock rates
were the same because they were getting
more parallelism at the lower levels of
the CPU implementation these CPUs
internals themselves were getting faster
in some cases they were getting smarter
in terms of being able to provide better
optimizations and they were getting more
parallelism so they're able to do more
things at the same time mm-hmm so so so
and they were doing a whole bunch of
other things but but effectively the
CPUs are just getting better even though
they're not getting faster and we don't
know I don't personally know when this
is going to end I don't follow CPUs as
much as Martin does so you can ask him
that when you talk to him you know but
to me I don't think CPU power and in my
experience CPU power hasn't been an
issue for 15 years or more
you mentioned memory that is not keeping
pace but will have another type of
memory so secondary memory is improving
dramatically over the years with right
SSD and similar technologies yes this
effect application performance is
something which
take into account how we tune how we
know device architectures for no
secondary memory you still got a problem
you got to get the data from that thing
that's very very far away to someplace
close right like you got to get it into
the CPU and so the primary bottleneck is
and always has been you know getting it
from memory into the CPU or right I
getting it off the bus into the CPU and
as you can see that that bus clock speed
hasn't really been changing until
recently we had a you know we had a jump
but you know prior to that it's been
fairly constant if you look at you know
disk performance the compared to SSD
performance yeah generally it's better
for a lot of cases but I mean I did a
test with a with a guy a while back I
said here we both have the same movie ie
big file I said let's just copy it you
have a hard disk right I have an SSD
let's dip it and we'll just see who gets
the cursor back first and the cursor
came back close enough on both machines
that that you know I wasn't able to say
that the SSD was faster than the hard
disk or the hard disk goes faster than
the SSD but was sequential axis that was
a sequential access axis that's where an
SSD can Excel know it depends and you
can find in non-sequential access that
sometimes the hard disk will do almost
as well as an SSD sort of it's sort of
non-intuitive so I I don't think that
these things are really making a
difference in terms of how you should
think about your application you should
just think of it that I'm gonna do an
i/o operation and my path my path from
my application down to whatever device
it is is this long it's yay long I go
through you know an app
patien buffer maybe several application
buffers depending on how we marshal the
data down to finally to an OS buffer to
maybe some internal disk buffers to
finally maybe I get onto the drive be it
SSD or not SSD right and so if you look
at how if you look at that I mean that
tends to be whatever called the
dominating cost in the entire that in
the entire process and these will always
be expensive and this will always be
expensive mm-hmm right one other thing
we can do is load lots of data nowadays
into Ram we have tens of gigabytes of
RAM so that's another alternative rather
than doing disk processing is this an
avenue that yeah that's interesting
that's a very interesting Avenue
actually the it's it's a funny one too
the the the the coherence guys set up a
cluster where no machine in the cluster
had a disk right and you might think
that it's like okay well that's crazy
how do you persist any everything right
and the answer was nothing was persisted
which might seem risky but I didn't have
my bank to do that what's that I
wouldn't want my bank to do that
actually was a bank doing it and so so
so and here's a reality situation you're
going like whoa no you don't wanna do
that and it's like I'm like well let's
do some math on this first off they had
everything replicated and they had a
partitioned so so the data was all
replicated multiple times and it was
partitioned and they had things to
basically make sure everything was in
sync they had the power lines you know
basically all set up so they even if
they had multiple failures on power
everything would be okay and you know
when it finally got to the hardware they
just took the disk out and what they
found is that made the hardware more
reliable in the sense that they had
fewer failures which actually makes
sense because if you think about the
most failure prone component on your
system it's in the kind of code one the
disk even the SS nice
ssds where and you know there were
problems okay so so cool so we just took
the most unstable component out of the
computer so what does that do to the
reliability numbers mm-hmm increases up
yeah yes problem solved not as easily
like main memory computation is
something that you think is a way
forward for some types of applications
correct yeah I think until we solved the
memory CPU Bonnell a key issue which
will be solved yeah keeping stuff in
memory keeping in cache improving cash
line densities and there's a whole bunch
of different things like that
I think will be essential if you're at
the high end performance you know high
performance the end of the spectrum for
most applications it's it's these types
of issues are are not important because
you have other things that are just much
much much bigger consumers of the of the
overall time budget mm-hmm it's close
with some overall discussion so what's
there now number one mistakes developers
do regarding optimization which is
something that you often see just
optimizing prematurely thinking I I can
just give you an example we were working
on a pricing engine once and the guys
responsible for the internal algorithm
realized it needed to be super super
super super fast but we didn't have
proper requirements from the customer
also so they were gonna so they went
into Donald Knuth you know wonderful
data structure books and pulled out this
quadtree complicated thingy and they're
you know basically scratching their
heads trying to figure out how to
implement this exceptionally complex
data structure and I looked at them I
said you guys are crazy our first
implementation should be throw away
because we don't have requirements
mm-hmm and because we don't have
requirements anything we give them is
going to be wrong and they're good but
by giving them something we're gonna
they're gonna tell us what's wrong
and
afterwards if we need that thing to go
fast and we have all the requirements
then we can look at implementing the
ultra expensive complex you know funky
quadtree thing to satisfy the SLA as you
mentioned earlier on too fast aside it
to satisfy the SLA is assuming simple
implementation didn't do it mm-hmm and
the converse side
what's your the optimization that
delivers the most positive results so
where should people start or what's
giving the most bang for the buck
it depends on what your problem is it's
so generally some things that people
miss is they don't do a proper GC tuning
you know as soon as you deploy you
should have something built in the
schedule that basically says now we need
to tune the garbage collectors so that's
probably the simple thing that people
miss dead I think so after a deployment
it's sort of like one of the last
configurations you do is you just say
okay you know now how is the garbage
collector performing and you know what
can we do to to cope with that the one
topic we haven't talked touched about
and possibly is is kind of interesting
is where we considered the future of
performance tuning and what future
tooling would look like mm-hm and this
is where we actually see artificial
intelligence actually starting to play
an important role so this is something
that we've actually been working on for
a number of years now is how do we make
diagnostic engines that are intelligent
and can adapt to conditions a diet do
diagnosis in when problems appear that
are much more complete than what you get
with the you know simple profilers and
things like that we want these things to
be able to run in production
environments we need them to be able to
run in in toxic environments so this is
what we've been working on would you
trust them to do that not only do we
trust them we have served
customers that are trusting them to do
this and we've been finding interesting
problems that we didn't recognize that
there didn't consider that the engine
would actually pick up on and our engine
is still what I would call fairly
immature so I mean if you stack us up
against a traditional tool we come up
very light you know currently in terms
of features but we're slowly building
this thing out and and what we're
finding is that you know we with the
proper modeling and the proper model in
front we can apply a AI techniques and
numerical analysis techniques to systems
and we can actually come up with very
very good diagnosis of performance
regressions generally in less than 20
seconds so something that might take me
an hour so assuming all of the tools and
the environments cooperate to diagnose
you know generally the tooling our
tooling can find that within about 20
seconds this sounds like an exciting
development 92% of the time all right
thank you very much for being with us
we're kind of listeners find more about
the topics we discussed well we run a
blog at Jake clarity we have friends of
Jay clarity so since I mentioned Martin
here I guess I need to give his mailing
list a plug which is mechanical sympathy
I think you'll find that there's a ton
of really smart people on his list as
well as ours I think a lot of them sure
you know participate in both lists and
and you know get involved with OpenJDK
if you're monitoring the mailing lists
and you're gonna see what's going on at
that level which can often be helpful
thank you very much again thank you for
having me this is the Amidah Spinelli's
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening thanks for listening the
SC radio an educational program brought
to you by Archer police software
magazine for more about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SC radio net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack channel at SC radio.com you
can also email us at team @ SC - radio
net this and all other episodes of se
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening